American Psychological Association Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
American Psychological Association Records 1917-1986 1940-1980
MSS51730
American Psychological Association
270,000 items
725 containers
290 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Professional organization for psychologists founded in 1892 to advance psychology as a science, as a profession, and as a means of promoting human welfare. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, drafts of books, articles, and lectures, congressional testimony, reports, agendas, ballots, financial data, printed matter, and other records chiefly documenting the organization and management of the association's boards, committees, and publications. Includes the personal records of some of its executives.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Albee, George W.--Correspondence.; Brayfield, Arthur H., 1915-2002--Correspondence.; Brayfield, Arthur H., 1915-2002. Arthur H. Brayfield papers.; Centor, Arthur--Correspondence.; Chein, Isidor, 1912-1981--Correspondence.; Clark, Kenneth Bancroft, 1914-2005--Correspondence.; Clendenen, Dorothy--Correspondence.; Darley, John Gordon, 1910-1990--Correspondence.; Hobbs, Nicholas--Correspondence.; Hoch, Erasmus Leonard, 1914- --Correspondence.; Hunt, John McVee--Correspondence.; Hunt, Thelma--Correspondence.; Little, Kenneth B., 1918-1997--Correspondence.; Little, Kenneth B., 1918-1997. Kenneth B. Little papers.; Margolin, Joseph B., 1921-2006--Correspondence.; McKeachie, Wilbert James, 1921- --Correspondence.; McMillan, John H.--Correspondence.; Olson, Willard Clifford, 1899-1978--Correspondence.; Olson, Willard Clifford, 1899-1978. Willard Clifford Olson papers.; Paterson, Donald G. (Donald Gildersleeve), 1892-1961. Donald Gildersleeve Paterson papers.; Sanford, Fillmore H. (Fillmore Hargrave), 1914-1967--Correspondence.; Tyler, Leona E. (Leona Elizabeth), 1906-1993--Correspondence.; Wolfle, Dael, 1906-2002--Correspondence.; Yerkes, Robert Mearns, 1876-1956--Correspondence.; Zaro, Joan S.
Organizations
American Psychological Association.; Peace Corps (U.S.)
Subjects
Aging.; Birth control.; Drug abuse.; Ethics.; Forensic psychology.; Homosexuality.; Loyalty oaths.; Mental health insurance.; Minorities.; Psychiatry.; Psychological tests.; Psychologists--Licenses.; Psychologists--Professional ethics.; Psychologists.; Psychology and religion.; Psychology--Societies, etc.; Psychology.; Science--Study and teaching.; Sex role.; Social justice.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Veterans.; Women.
Acquisition Information
The records of the American Psychological Association were given to the Library of Congress between 1967 and 1986.
Transfers
A phonodisc sound recording and recordings of oral history interviews have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these records.
Other Repositories
Other records of the American Psychological Association are located at the Akron University Psychological Archives, Akron, Ohio.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the American Psychological Association are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Note on the Organization
Founded in 1892 and incorporated in 1925, the American Psychological Association (APA), a professional organization for psychologists, numbered slightly over seventy-two thousand members as of 1991. The primary purpose of the organization, according to Article I of the original articles of incorporation, is "to advance psychology as a science, as a profession, and as a means of promoting human welfare." These objectives are accomplished through annual meetings, through publication of journals, pamphlets and books, and through administrative services that strive to improve standards and training for psychologists.
The chief governing body of the APA is the Council of Representatives, whose members include representatives from each of the association's divisions and affiliated state associations. The Board of Directors is the administrative agent of the council and exercises general supervision over the affairs of the association through interaction with the executive officer. The board is composed of six council members elected by the council and six officers of the association (president, past president, president-elect, recording secretary, treasurer, and executive officer). The executive officer does not vote.
The administration of the organization is vested in the executive officer, at various times called the executive secretary, executive officer and chief executive officer, who manages the central office located in Washington, D. C. Adjuncts to the executive are a number of specialized administrative offices that support the administrator according to the interests of the office. For instance, there are offices dealing with educational affairs, scientific affairs, women's issues, and professional affairs.
Associated with the organization are divisions, committees, and affiliated organizations that help define the interests of the association. Presently the APA has forty-two divisions, ranging from "general psychology" and "psychologists in private practice," to "counseling," "teaching of psychology," "personality," and "family." Committees guide projects and handle issues ranging from ethical standards to insurance and financial questions. Some committees are standing bodies; others are continuing or ad hoc. Committees are established by the council of representatives, board, or other committees. Affiliates are organizations that have merged or associated with the APA. One such group represented in the records is the American Association of Applied Psychologists.
Information on the formative period of the organization is contained in an article by Samuel W. Fernberger, published in the Psychological Bulletin in 1932, detailing its history from 1892 to the early 1930s.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the American Psychological Association (APA) span the years 1917-1986, with the bulk of the records concentrated in the period 1940-1980. The records consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, agenda, ballots, financial records, drafts of books, articles, and lectures, testimonies, printed and near printed matter, and miscellaneous material. The collection is organized into eight series representing the structure and function of the organization, including Council of Representatives, Board of Directors, Administration, Boards and Committees, Divisions, Journals and Publications, and Affiliated Organizations, as well as a Miscellany file. The records are replete with gaps. A lack of consistency in the retirement of APA records may have contributed to the absence of material regarding certain periods or subjects. Many divisions and committees did not retire their records to the Library of Congress, preferring the Akron University Psychological Archives in Akron, Ohio. The records of the APA held by that institution should be consulted where gaps exist here.
The governing bodies of the APA – the Council of Representatives and Board of Directors – are represented in these records by separate series dating between the end of World War II and the beginning of the 1980s. Consisting largely of correspondence, memoranda, reports, and meeting data, these series treat business and organizational issues and relate to the professional direction of the association.
More extensive in scope and chronology is the Administration file. Until 1955, much of the material in the records of the APA was maintained in the office files of the executive secretary of the association. Dating primarily from the 1930s, the Executive Officers File in the Administration series reflects the managerial decisions of the organization's chief officers and documents its main activities. Featured in the personal records of various executives – from Donald Gildersleeve Paterson and Willard Clifford Olson in the 1930s and 1940s to Arthur H. Brayfield and Kenneth B. Little in the 1960s and 1970s – are the concerns and issues that defined their tenure as leaders. Themes of significance include APA-government relations, psychological testing, forensic information, loyalty investigations, the behavioral sciences, scientific exchanges, science and education, and the Peace Corps. Other important issues include legislation on aging, television projects, legal testimony, White House conferences, international cooperation, and ongoing publication efforts.
Also in the Administration series are Departmental Offices Files relating to the principal subdivisions in the association, including the Educational Affairs Office, Professional Affairs Office, Programs and Planning Office, Scientific Affairs Office, and Women's Program. In subject matter, they document the thrust of the APA's post-1950s operations from the minutia of daily activities to the practical applications of its programs and policies. As an example, within the files of the Professional Affairs Office are studies concerning abortion, contraception, population issues, and social attitudes, all under the term "family planning."
The Boards and Committees series offers further documentation of APA's outreach in developing and promoting psychology as a profession and field of study. Principal groups represented are boards relating to professional affairs, scientific affairs, social and ethical responsibility, education and training, and publication. Featured as well are the files of temporary bodies or continuing committees such as boards on ethical standards in psychological research, on psychology in governmental and public affairs, on revision of test standards, and on the APA's association with the guilds of related disciplines.
Topics highlighted in the Boards and Committees series reflect the core concerns of the organization, especially after 1960. Prominent are women's issues, equal opportunity for minorities, drug use, attitudes concerning sexual orientation, Vietnam War veterans, post-doctoral education, sex-role stereotyping, and social justice. Particularly extensive are files relating to the ethical treatment of human subjects during research. Also significant are testing and training questions and problems. Health issues are prominent throughout the collection, from licensing considerations and insurance matters to community health centers and the relationship between psychology and psychiatry.
The remaining files of the APA consist of a large Divisions series, followed by Journals and Publications, Affiliated Organizations, and a small Miscellany. Eclectic and incomplete, the Divisions series is organized by number of division, but the numbering is inconsistent and not all divisions are represented in the records. The files for Divisions 12, 14, and 17 ("Clinical," "Industrial" and "Counseling Psychology") are the most complete.
The records in the Journals and Publications series are also fragmentary, with the stronger portion beginning in the 1970s. Included are editorial and administrative matter related to books, abstracts, monographs, and journals published by the organization.
The Affiliated Organizations series consists of files relating to the American Association for Applied Psychology, the Conference of State Psychological Associations, and the Virginia Psychological Association, which beginning in the 1940s affiliated with the APA.
Among the prominent or frequent correspondents in the collection are George Albee, Arthur H. Brayfield, Arthur Centor, Isador Chein, Kenneth Bancroft Clark, Dorothy Clendenen, John Gordon Darley, Nicholas Hobbs, Erasmus Leonard Hoch, John McVee Hunt, Thelma Hunt, Kenneth B. Little, Joseph B. Margolin, Wilbert James McKeachie, John H. McMillan, Willard Clifford Olson, Fillmore H. Sanford, Leona Elizabeth Tyler, Dael Lee Wolfle, Robert Mearns Yerkes, and Joan S. Zaro.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Council of Representatives, 1945-1986
Board of Directors, 1946-1986
Administration, 1918-1985
Boards and Committees, 1920-1986
Divisions, 1917-1985
Journals and Publications, 1925-1986
Affiliated Organizations, 1932-1984
Miscellany, 1931-1986
Container List
- Council of Representatives, 1945-1986 (Box 1-8)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, ballots, budgetary and financial matters, reports, rules of council, and recommendations.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and thereunder chronologically.
  - Agenda, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting
    - June 1946-June 1951, (9 folders)
    - July 1951-April 1953, (9 folders) (Box 2)
    - May 1953-June 1956, (9 folders) (Box 3)
    - July-Dec. 1956 (Box 4)
  - Ballots
    - June 1947-May 1956, (5 folders)
    - June 1956-Feb. 1973, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Business meetings
    - Sept. 1958
    - Sept. 1965
    - 10-12 Mar. 1966
      - Agenda and related material
      - Correspondence
        - Individuals, (2 folders)
        - State psychological associations
      - Minutes, 1956-1966
      - Reports, 1956-1965, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Career changes and retraining, 1982
  - Council action, 1960-1969
  - General correspondence
    - 1945-1949, (5 folders)
    - 1950-1956, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Memoranda (1955-1963)
  - Preliminary budget, 1983
  - Recommendations from Board of Directors, 1951
  - Reports
    - 1946-1954, (3 folders)
    - 1955-1957, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Rules of council, 1960-1968, (5 folders)
  - Washington reports, 1965
- Board of Directors, 1946-1986 (Box 9-28)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, agendas, ballots, newspaper clippings, minutes of meetings, and miscellaneous material.
  Organized by type or topic of material.
  - General correspondence (Box 9)
    - Oct. 1946-Aug. 1949, (5 folders)
    - Sept. 1949-Aug. 1950, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - Sept. 1950-Sept. 1954, (10 folders) (Box 11)
    - Oct. 1954-Nov. 1957, (10 folders) (Box 12)
    - Feb. 1958-June 1975, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Memoranda
    - Jan.-June 1958
    - July 1958-Feb. 1963, (4 folders) (Box 14)
    - Oct. 1963-May 1967, 1981, undated, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Meetings
    - Agenda
      - Sept. 1946-Sept. 1950, (2 folders)
      - Mar. 1951-May 1954, (4 folders) (Box 16)
      - Aug.-Sept. 1954, annual meeting
      - May 1955-Sept. 1958, (3 folders) (Box 17)
      - Aug.-Sept. 1963, annual meeting
      - Sept. 1964, annual meeting (Box 18)
      - Sept. 1965, annual meeting
      - Oct. 1966-Jan. 1981, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 19)
      - Supplemental agenda, 1963-1964
    - Ballots
      - Nov. 1946-Aug. 1948, (2 folders)
      - Mar. 1949-May 1953, (5 folders) (Box 20)
      - July 1953-Apr. 1954, (4 folders) (Box 21)
      - May 1954-Oct. 1956, (4 folders) (Box 22)
        - Ballots I, 1956-1957
        - Ballots II, 1956-1957 (Box 23)
      - Jan. 1957-Aug. 1958
    - Clippings, 1948
    - Minutes
      - Mar. 1947-Sept. 1953, (4 folders)
      - Apr. 1954-May 1966, 1983, (4 folders) (Box 24)
    - Reports
      - Sept. 1949-Aug. 1952, (2 folders)
      - Mar. 1953-July 1955, (5 folders) (Box 25)
      - Aug. 1955-Dec. 1958, (6 folders) (Box 26)
      - Jan. 1959-May 1969, (5 folders) (Box 27)
      - Non-APA
        - May 1948-Aug. 1950
        - Oct. 1951-July 1959, (3 folders) (Box 28)
  - Subject file
    - Constitutional issues, 1965
    - Ernst and Ernst, 1962-1963, (2 folders)
    - In-house counsel, 1977-1979
    - International Union of Scientific Psychology, 1960
    - Newman, Sidney H., 1965
- Administration, 1918-1985 (Box 29-292)
  - Executive Officers File, 1918-1978 (Box 29-132)
    Correspondence, memoranda, reports, administrative material, and subject files of the administrative officers of the APA Central Office.
    Organized according to five offices or positions - executive secretary, executive officer, president, president-elect, and recording secretary - and therein chronologically by officeholder, with further subdivisions arranged alphabetically by type or subject of material.
    - Executive secretary (Box 29)
      - Donald Gildersleeve Paterson
        - Correspondence, A-Y, 1930-1952, (9 folders)
        - Subject file, 1924-1937
          - Association of Consulting Psychologists, 1933-1937, (2 folders)
          - Century of Progress Exposition, Chicago, Ill., 1932-1934 (Box 30)
          - International Congress of Psychologists, 1931-1937
          - Jewish psychologists in Germany, 1933
          - Langfeld, Herbert S., correspondence, 1937
          - Meyer, Max F., resolution on, 1933
          - Nominations, 1933
          - Psychological Review, 1924-1935
          - Psychology departments, evaluations, 1933
          - Psychometric Society, 1935-1936
          - Siegel, Abraham, 1934
          - Yerkes proposal, recognizing J. M. Cattrell, 1928-1935
      - Willard Clifford Olson
        - General administrative file
          - Academy of Foreign Relations, 1938
          - Accounts and finances, taxes, 1942
          - Advisory Committee on Scientific Personnel,1945
          - American Association for an International Office of Education, 1944
          - American Association for Applied Psychology
            - Dues collected, 1944-1945
            - General, 1939-1946, (3 folders)
            - Invitations-refusals, 1944-1945
            - Merger with APA, 1944-1946
            - Transfers in merger, 1945 (Box 31)
          - American Association for the Advancement of Science,1941-1945, (2 folders)
          - American Bar Association, criminal law, 1938
          - American Chemical Society, 1943
          - American College Personnel Association, 1945
          - American Council on Education, 1937-1946
          - American Documentation Institute, 1940-1946
        - American Journal of Psychology, 1940-1941
          - American Men of Science, 1944
          - American Standards Association, 1940-1945
          - American Teachers' Association, 1942-1943
          - Annual report of the treasurer and business manager, 1944
          - Archives of Psychology, 1945
          - Badges, 1940-1945
          - Board of Directors, 1945
          - Board of Editors, 1942-1945, (2 folders) (Box 32)
          - Brazil Psychological Center, 1939
          - Brigham, C. C., correspondence, 1931
          - Calendar for office, 1945
          - California Association for Applied Psychologists, 1940-1942
          - Chicago Psychological Club, Chicago, Ill.,1941-1944
          - Cincinnati Psychological Club, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1941-1945
          - Committee for National Morale
            - Bibliography, 1939-1941
            - Conference, 1940
            - General
              - 1940
              - 1941-1942 (Box 33)
            - Reports
              - 1918-1941, (3 folders)
              - 1942-1945, (2 folders) (Box 34)
          - Committee on Audio-Visual Aids, 1940-1945
          - Committee on Central Office, 1945
          - Committee on Child Development, 1943
          - Committee on Clinic Certification, 1941-1942
          - Committee on Clinical Psychology, 1944-1945
          - Committee on College Curriculum Adjustments
            - 1942-1943
          - Committee on Committees, 1945
          - Committee on Costs, 1936-1937
          - Committee on Division Organization, 1944-1945
          - Committee on Extension of Functions of Secretary's Office
            - Apr. 1933-June 1941
            - July 1941-Mar. 1943 (Box 35)
          - Committee on Graduate and Professional Training in Psychology, 1944-1945, (2 folders)
          - Committee on Internal Planning in Psychology, 1944-1945
          - Committee on Investments, 1940-1945
          - Committee on Latin American Psychology, 1940-1942
          - Committee on Official Journal, 1944-1945
          - Committee on Precautions in Animal Experimentation, 1940-1945
          - Committee on Psychology and Public Service, 1942
          - Committee on Publications, 1945
          - Committee on Publicity and Public Relations, 1933-1946, (3 folders)
          - Committee on Qualifications for Industrial Psychology, 1936-1942
          - Committee on Scientific and Professional Ethics, 1943-1945, (2 folders) (Box 36)
          - Committee on Standards for Psychological Service Centers, 1944-1945
          - Committee on Surplus War Materials, 1946-1947
          - Committee on the Constitution, 1940-1945, (2 folders)
          - Committee on the Observance of the Fiftieth Anniversary of the APA and the Centennial of William James, 1940-1943
          - Committee on the Preparation of Examination Questions in Psychology, 1940-1945, (2 folders)
          - Committee on Titles and Content of Courses in Psychology, 1941-1943
          - Committee on Utilization in Psychology of Surplus War Materials, 1944-1945
          - Committee on War Services to Children, 1940-1944
          - Connecticut Valley Association of Psychologists, 1941-1944
          - Convention Program Committee, 1937-1942 (Box 37)
          - Council meeting, 1945
          - Department of Psychology of the American Teachers' Association, 1938-1945
          - Department of the Navy, Office of Naval Research, 1947-1957
          - Department of the Treasury, Commissioner of Internal Revenue, 1938-1943
          - Divisions within the APA
            - Division 9: Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, 1936-1945, (2 folders)
              - General, 1945
          - Eastern Psychological Association, 1940-1945
          - Election Committee, 1938-1941
          - Election to membership, 1938-1945
          - Eligibility list for voting, 1945
          - Emergency Committee in Psychology of the National Research Council, 1944-1945
          - Executive Committee, 1940-1945, (2 folders) (Box 38)
          - Financial statements, 1941-1946
          - Future meetings, 1945
          - Garrett, Henry E., 1945
          - Government agencies
            - Department of Labor, 1946
            - Federal Security Agency, Office of Vocational Rehabilitation, 1943-1952
            - United States Civil Service Commission, 1938-1943
            - Veterans Administration, 1944-1946
          - History of the APA, 1940
          - Illinois Society of Consulting Psychologists, 1938-1944
          - Inaugurations and celebrations, 1944-1945
          - Indiana Association of Clinical Psychologists, 1938-1945
          - International Congress of Psychology, 1938-1940
          - Inter-Society Color Council, 1931-1946
          - Inter-Society Constitutional Convention
            - 1942
            - 1943 (Box 39)
          - Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology, 1940-1943
          - Journal of Applied Psychology, 1942-1944
          - Journal of Experimental Psychology, 1945
          - Library of Congress, 1939-1946
          - Life membership requests, 1938-1945
          - Metropolitan New York Association for Applied Psychology, 1939-1944
          - Michigan Psychological Association, 1940-1944
          - Michigan State Board of Tax Administration, 1942
          - Midwestern Psychological Association, 1938-1945
          - Milwaukee Psychological Club, 1939-1944
          - Minnesota Society for Applied Psychology, 1937-1944
          - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1937-1945
          - Nanson ballot counting system, 1942-1943
          - National Committee on Education and Defense, 1940-1943
          - National Council of Scientific, Professional, Art, and White Collar Organizations, 1944-1945